howdy this is Jim rut and this is the
Jim rut show listeners have asked us to
provide pointers some of the resources
we talked about on the show we now have
links to books and articles referenced
in recent podcasts that are available on
our website
we also offer full transcripts so - Jim
rut show.com that's Jim ruts show com
today's guest is Zach Stein writer
educator and futurist working to bring a
greater sense of sanity and justice to
education it's good to be here
yeah it's interesting that we haven't
connected earlier I guess we did
actually connect many years ago but you
know we kind of travel in similar
circles online and we know a lot of the
same people so it's really great to have
you on the show and be able to get into
your work in some depth
Zach studied philosophy and religion at
Hampshire College and this is
interesting
zach is now the third Hampshire College
Grad I've had on my show the statistical
unlikeliness of that is really unlikely
the first one was least small on the
physicist I don't remember who the
second one was if I remember pointing it
out that it was statistically unusual to
have two and now we have three something
interesting about Hampshire College
after Hampshire College Zach studied
educational neuroscience human
development the philosophy of education
at Harvard is a co-founder of electic
a-- a not-for-profit dedicated to
research-based justice oriented reform
of large-scale standardized testing in
k-12 higher education and business he's
also on various boards of various early
stage and not-for-profits got his hands
into various things in this area we're
mostly going to talk about Zac's book
education in a time between worlds links
to the book and other resources we
discussed will as always be available on
Zach's episode page at Jim Rutte show
calm let's start with the title I
usually don't talk about the title much
but the title I thought was a vaca t'v
education in a time between world
could you unpack time between worlds a
little bit totally yeah I did a basic
idea I mean it's a few things combined
you know one of them is just actually a
very theoretical idea from the field of
world Systems Theory which is founded by
Immanuel Wallerstein and he had this
notion that there were within the
history of the capitalist world system
these periods when there were economic
rollovers when basically the long time a
demonic force which dominated the world
system goes into decay and there's a
kind of period where there's not a clear
overarching order to the world system
until another one locks in and so these
were world system transformations and
what's interesting is that these
actually align historically in terms of
the epochs with other models like models
from cultural evolution where you're
looking at the movement out of the you
know late pre-modern to the early modern
and then from the early modern to the
like mature modern and then for the
mature modern to the postmodern and
there's several different halls
including esoteric models from people
like Rudolf Steiner where you're looking
at this notion that there are periods
when although we're still on the same
earth we are moving to a different world
and we are in one of those periods right
now and basically when you're in where
those periods education itself becomes
one of the primary vectors of kind of
collapsing the new world into into order
and so that's the way I'm kind of
framing the educational thinking I'm
doing in the book which is to say this
isn't the thinking I would have been
doing back in like the 1950s or 60s let
alone 1890s or something like this is
the thinking you do when you're
literally between worlds when you are
trying to reboot a very basic human
for structure like a hard reboot and so
obviously you can see how this links
into the thinking around game B and
there's other groups that are holding
similar notions so then that's a little
bit about that notion of the between
worlds yeah we'll talk about that a
little bit later in fact and I'll just
point people to my essay in search of
the fifth attractor which talks about
the fact that the ball is gonna fly out
of our basin at some point and we all
have a moral duty to make sure it lands
in a good basin and not a bad one I
think we're all on the same mission here
essentially we're gonna start off again
a little unusually because you use some
terms which may not be generally
understood by folks in the wider world
by no means is all my audience the game
B world there's lots of academics and
businesspeople and just regular old
folks that listen one of the things you
say is that you see the central
importance of education as an aspect of
the global meta crisis could you unpack
the idea of meta-crisis a little bit
totally so there's a there's a few ways
to think of it and there's a few
different people doing work on it so I'm
gonna give my view you can think of it
in a couple ways one is that there are
many crises and if you so for example
there's something like an ecological
crisis right there's something like a
geopolitical crisis there's something
like a local political crisis at the
level of American democracy there's
something like a crisis in the schools
and the health care so like take your
pick
you could characterize the fields as
crisis ridden and that's in part because
of the time between worlds notion but if
you take the kid all the crises combined
you get a super ordinate crisis which is
the meadow crisis you could think of
that as potentially being distilled into
the generator function behind all of the
crises why are they all occurring but
you can also think of that meta crisis
as specifically educational which is to
say if you're in the woods and you get
lost that's a crisis and then if it gets
cold and you have to make a fire that's
another crisis if you don't know how
make a fire but the meta-crisis there is
actually your own mind it's actually the
state of your skills and your ability to
keep your head on your shoulders so
that's the crisis behind the crisis and
so in a sense the educational crisis is
pivotal within the broader meta crisis
because it's the one that gets at the
heart of the issue which is the nature
of human choice making self
understanding and capacity so when you
look at the situation I'm seeing several
things in that light you're seeing a
capabilities crisis which is to say the
the things we need to figure out how to
do who are not figuring out just jump in
and say essentially capability versus
complexity problem right exactly
we actually have more capability now
than we did in 1850 but we're
confronting a much more complex world so
it's really a mismatch between
exponentially rising complexity and you
know probably also exponentially rising
capability but rising on a lower
exponential yeah that's right the we've
we've ended up building a civilization
where the the problems we're confronting
have become so complex so quickly that
there's a lag in the human capacity
upgrade needed to meet them so that's
your classic that's one classic
dimension of educational crisis as kind
of the meta crisis here their capability
crisis but there's also a legitimation
crisis right and this is also a
dimension of the educational crisis
which is to say that it's not just that
we can't figure stuff out from a
capability to standpoint we can't figure
out who is the one with the legitimate
Authority even say they figured it out
right so this is touching on the
political crisis but it's even deeper
because it's about the legitimacy of
authority period the lack of social
cohesion or social capital you know is
one of the very strong amplifiers of the
meta-crisis because obviously it
undermines the ability to you know
organize serious attacks on the
meta-crisis I mean just look at the
clown-like response of the United States
to the cover
virus you know compare and contrast was
say our response to World War two or the
Cuban Missile Crisis exactly and when
you're looking at it from the
perspective of the schools that ship
sailed a long time ago there's been an
absence of legitimate teach really
Authority in the schools and
universities for quite a while and so
that is what has produced the more
widespread sense of illegitimate across
most of our major institutions so but
then you also have the meaning crisis
which is adjacent to the legitimacy
crisis and the capability crisis which
is basically what a lot of work for
baekje talks about in others where it's
it's not just there's not legitimate
Authority and there's problems that are
too complex to solve there's also a
sense of we don't know what we're about
as a species or a nation or even an
individual what's the meaning of the
suffering what's the meaning of the joy
what's the meaning of death sleep dreams
there's such a dimension of cultural
incoherence here this is part of what
the conspiracy theory industrial complex
plugs into is the opening the question
mark in the place where there should be
actual meaning and then the final ones
in intelligibility crisis which is to
say and this is different than a
capability crisis because it's not about
if we're able to do anything it's about
if we're able to understand anything at
the level of like cognitive sense making
this a sense making crisis we just also
talked about like like people like
Jordan Hall is a friend of mine so those
are the four you've got the sense making
crisis the legitimacy crisis the meaning
crisis and the capability crisis and
that's all on the what's sometimes
called the interior T's of civilization
which is to say these aren't
infrastructure failures they're the
condition for the possibility of
infrastructure failures they're not
political breakdowns they're the
condition for the possibility of
political breakdowns there prior to them
because they reside within the human
psyche and body
and so they're there the within and
there what they need to be grappled with
in the dimension of consciousness
learning human development education
they're not technical problems and so
that is why I believe although education
like you know I went to the Harvard
Graduate School of Education which
believe me is the low end of the totem
pole when it comes to the graduate
schools of education at Harvard right so
the amount of importance that's placed
on education the marginalization of it
visa fees of the Law School in the
Kennedy School of Government and the God
the Business School
these things are funded to the hilt full
rides for PhD students whereas the
Graduate School of Education students
are going into hundreds of thousands of
dollars of student loan debt so there's
this question of why given the primacy
condition for the possibility of
failures across all external systems are
the interior systems why education is so
important has it been so neglected and
actually at this point it is being
preyed upon by forces seeking to profit
from the obvious crisis of capability
the generosity of meaning predatory
student loan lending being the main one
but also the overwhelming push to
privatize the schools that make them
profit centers in the same way that
hospitals were made profit centers so
yeah that's a little bit more there
about just when it comes to the
meta-crisis the sharp end of the stick
is actually within our own minds and the
educational system has been so poorly
managed since about 1972 that were
looking at a potential catastrophic
breakdown of intergenerational
transmission and sintering I graduate
from high school in 1971 and it was a
working class high school my zip code
later looked up in the demographic data
in 1970 50 percent of the adults were
high school dropouts
about 50 percent had high school
education and like to percent had
college degrees and yet it was a great
school you know I had a really good
education went to an elite college MIT
and I would say I was better prepared
than the average fancy suburbanite who I
was competing with and even the prep
schoolers and yet you go back to that
same high school today and his really is
really failing for all kinds of reasons
I've got the sense that somewhere around
in the 70s and you know we talked in the
game be world at 1975 was when the
ethics of business fundamentally changed
when there were limits on what people
would do and in fact when Jordan Hall
and I first met I don't know how long
fourteen years ago at a board meeting at
the Santa Fe Institute our first
conversation was about just that me
being almost exactly one generation
older than him I was saying hey when I
joined the business world I was
fortunate to have worked for some
relatively ethical companies and they
would actually talk about what they
would or would not do that was legal
within their domain but was they thought
wrong and Jordan said when he entered
the workplace in the mid 90s the rule
had changed to the outer edge of what is
permissible in the business world is
what is arguably legal not necessarily
right or wrong and then we both agreed
that by the time we were talking in 2008
it had gone another step to what should
be done in business is what can you can
get away with or where the penalties for
getting caught are smaller than the
winds right think about Facebook and its
violations of its promises and so you
know there's sort of a fundamental
change that was started to be visible at
least around 1975 in the ethical
operating systems of our society and you
know culture is built in schools and in
families and so somebody is failing to
do their job to build the right kinds of
people to operate our society and that's
certainly one of the key parts of the
meta-crisis one more bit of definition
it's not really definition let's just
hop into it and call it substance one of
the things that you call out quite
repeatedly in your book is to contrast
your ideas around education with what
you describe as the reductive human
capital theory might be useful to the
mind what you mean by the reductive
human capital theory and you know
contrast that at the highest possible
level with what you think we need yes a
human capital theories pretty well known
way of thinking about the way human
beings fit into economic reasoning and
decision-making and reductive human
capital theory is basically the most
kind of simplified and crude way of
thinking about this and so the basic
idea would be that human beings are like
any other kind of capital or commodity
and just like getting a bunch of money
allows you to do something you call a
capital if you get a bunch of skills it
allows you to do things so you can think
of skills residing within humans right
the interiors I was talking about you
can think of those as a form of capital
and then you conceive the educational
system as basically a sub component of
the broader economy with the sub
function of supplying that economy with
human capital and so you reduce the like
multifaceted
dimensions of intergenerational
transmission to 1 which is the
reproduction of the economic system and
that's reductive human capital theory
and basically it is to use 'shmock to
Berger's language it's a self
terminating protocol for an educational
system it actually undermines the other
aspects of culture which are the kind of
hidden curriculum within the economy
that actually allows it to function and
this is something that's been pointed
out by Marxists for a while
which is that yeah you think it's the
schools in the Ivy League universities
that prepare your workers and CEOs but
it's actually their mothers who aren't
paid at all so the hidden labor of human
development which has long been in the
domain of women and long completely
unrelated and long neglected and
actually preyed upon so it's not Jim
that the cultural transmission takes
place around the tables of the
and in the schools that's the case but
why are the schools and dinner tables
failing it's because of all the other
predatory systems that are increasingly
incursion increasingly colonizing the
life world so that when you're looking
at the human capital theory and you're
thinking well where the human capital
actually supplied from where do we
actually mine it we mined it in the
families first and then we mined it in
the schools and so you're actually
preying upon this necessary dimension of
intergenerational transmission and kind
of extracting from it this simplified
skill and capacity kind of mindset which
ends up in the long run undercutting the
dinner table and the substance of
schooling so that you get people who are
yeah they have skills but they have no
source of motivation they have no source
of creative thinking they have no
ethical compass and you were saying so
the over focusing on the efficiency of
the economy although it seems like a
good idea in the short term ends up
undermining the potential for
productivity in the long term because
you've destroyed all of the all of the
all the intangibles and you've
commodified all the stuff that actually
shouldn't be commodified so that's a
little bit about the human capital
theory which has been absolutely the
predominant way of thinking about
education like when you think about No
Child Left Behind and Obama's race to
the top and those kinds of models of
educational reform they're absolutely
dominated by human capital mentality you
save the schools to save the economy and
then similar to the global educational
reform movement sometimes called germ
G erm Gates Foundation etc into Africa
and other places similarly you're seeing
mostly the nature of the reforms
themselves held within this human
capital mindset which again reduces
education to lowest common denominator
need to reproduce the economics
them and and pushing into the margins
and actually kind of like offloading
externalities into the other dimensions
of intergenerational transmission which
are necessary like ethical and meaning
making and legitimacy so yeah that's
that's my that's my thinking there and
it is important not to actually blame
the schools or the mothers right when in
fact it is many of the institutions and
systems around the household in the
school which make it almost impossible
to do the right thing within them and
this is a point I make in my book in
several places especially the chapter on
social miracles which is that it's not
the schools they need to be reformed
it's the civilization that needs to be
reformed in order for us to have schools
that we actually want you know most of
the most well-meaning educational reform
projects fail not because it's
impossible to do what they want to do in
the schools but rather because it's
impossible to have a school like that in
a culture like ours and a society like
ours it's the classic look like well
that would be great thing to do for kids
that sounds wonderful but how could they
ever get a job
it's like saying oh if you and this is
one of Hampshire colleges problems if
you teach people to value meaningful
work and to hate bullshit and to not
vert you signal right and to not kind of
go to the lowest common denominator
profit motive types of incentives and
then you release them into the world to
get jobs where are they gonna go right
and so until we change the systems
around the educational system we can't
pretend that making changes to the
educational systems are really going to
do anything that's a key point that I
think is something that the audience
should internalize before we go further
because otherwise you could say I that
zactly he's a you know utopian screwball
that shit won't work but if you take it
in the consideration that we're talking
about it as a kind of a two-part motion
of Education with cultural and
institutional reforms that the two
eventually converge into a world where
they both make sense then we have
something I had a very similar
experience on Facebook yesterday where I
think I was actually Daniel Schumacher
and Berger posted a question on
what would policing of the future look
like and I put up my idea and someone
said that couldn't possibly work rabbits
were craziest thing I received certainly
in a world like ours right but my
response will be exactly you know my
ideas about policing and I come from a
police family my dad was a career police
officer my brother was - one of my
favorite cousins so I know a fair amount
about you know the sociology of police
from the ground floor my ideas of how to
do a great policing yeah they would not
work in our current society but that's
the point there's something wrong with
our current society because a good
ethical form of policing can't work in
the same sense that a good ethical form
of Education could not work in what we
would call in game be talk you know
advanced game a the hyper financialized
ratchet of status as consumerism factum
to go off a little bit and respond to
your talk about some of your comments
about the family structure and again
throw in a little personal history you
know my parents lived a you know lower
middle class and then gradually is sort
of a middle middle class like time I
graduated my high school my father was
making exactly the median family income
in the United States as a lieutenant in
the Washington DC Police Department and
my mother who's vastly more talented
than my father had chosen not to work
for money but she was very active as a
volunteer you know she ran the PTA she
ran the babysitting Club she later got
into politics and had eventually
extremely large-scale jobs in politics
including delegate to national
conventions you know being in charge of
all the women volunteers in the eastern
third of the country and one of the
presidential campaigns but always not
for pay and you know people would
sometimes say Marianne you know you
could be making the big bucks she got
well you know I want to I don't really
want to I don't care you know they they
were happy with who they were they were
not on the status via consumption
ratchet that sort of the later
generations who had been indoctrinated
by you know pervasive psychologically
astute TV advertising had drilled into
them so that now all the mothers I got
my mother despite having left home when
she was 14
could add a large lucrative paid career
but to her family and community and
volunteer work was way more satisfying
than being able to trade in our often
beter used cars for some fancy new car
you know our little 960 square foot
house for some big old thing she just
didn't think that stuff was important
and neither did my father and you know
that's unfortunately been programmed out
of most people today starting you know
with my generation the Boomers you know
most of us were pretty damn status des
consumerist from the get-go and it had
gotten worse since then though maybe
it's turning around a little bit with
the Millennials surprising number of
Millennials I've gotten to meet
particularly through local agricultural
work that I do kind of the modern this
time competent back-to-the-landers
unlike the 1974 crew from Hampshire
College and those involved in radical
social change and their friends seem
much less in the matrix of status
through consumption so you know that may
be a sign that there are some
opportunities here for us to bring in
this better world let me jump back to
one of the things you said twice and
that is the intergenerational
transmission of essential human
capacities for reason in reflection
could fail and when we talk about what
comes next
we hope what's one of the better worlds
but if this truly were to fail at a
fundamental fashion isn't it possible we
could have a serious collapse of the
fall of Rome sort
and that's what's happening it's not
that it could fail it's that that it is
failing and you you could argue that it
has failed and already and that we are
in and may be pretty far into collapse
dynamics that are at the end of the day
traceable to the fundamental breakdown
in intergenerational transmission as
basically as a result of the
colonization of the life world which is
precisely what you described in your you
know fascinating reflections on on your
mother and the transition into a new
generation who became status seeking and
then the transition again with the
Millennials into a generation who are
not status seeking through consumerism
but that is in part because they are
poor and that is in part because they
did not actually have the opportunities
for upward mobility that were provided
for the baby boomer generation and so
they've been saddled with student loan
debt student loan debt which the boomers
didn't have they've been facing a job
market which is saturated by baby
boomers at the highest levels who are
holding under jobs 20 years longer than
their parents did which is to say like
there hasn't actually been a turnover
generationally since the boomers took
over and they are prolonging that
seemingly indefinitely and there hasn't
been a turnover of resources or access
to power or wisdom / knowledge /
capacity and so that's just a striking
situation which is kind of having these
ramifications up and into the
meta-crisis so it is happening in the
you know the result is actually when it
starts to set in which is to say when
intergenerational transmission truly
fails you get a distance between the
elders and the youth that is so great
the only result can be strategic
relation which means generational
warfare and there were some mark
who believe that at the end of the day
class warfare would transform into
generational warfare there's a there's
reasons to see that as actually one of
the things that's playing out here when
you look at the nature of asset holding
and access to the halls of power that's
being hoarded by the boomers so I think
we're actually in the situation where we
are approximating generational warfare
and right now the Boomers are winning
it's amazing
yeah the boomers have had the presidency
since 1992 right interestingly Joe Biden
is actually a silent he is not a boomer
he came he's the very tail end of the
generation before the Boomers but
there's even a more extreme example of
the dynamic I'm talking about yeah what
the fuck right here you know in the 60s
you know being part of the sixties I was
part of a really violent upheaval which
I heard fair amount more secondhand than
primaries my time I got to college in 71
the previous four years had been when
the radical changes had come you know in
1967 at MIT
you know the dorms were strictly
monitored no girls allowed in the room
you know no drinking on campus blah blah
blah by 1971 the boomers had routed the
silence and the GI Joes and had totally
intimidated them and we basically ran
the goddamn place for both better in for
worse I mean I think it had some
negative consequences but we had
terrorized the older generation into
submission to our demands and by 1971
our dorm was wide open you want to have
your girlfriend over for the weekend no
problem you could we had to deal with a
local liquor store that would deliver
liquor to the front desk totally illegal
oh well and the boomers routed the
previous generations in an astoundingly
binary way between about 1967 and maybe
at the latest 1975 nothing like that has
happened at all right and we had our
first boomer president with Bill Clinton
when he was quite young so maybe the
Boomers learned from their victory how
not to be displaced we shall see yeah I
mean it's it's actually quite
striking and disturbing when you think
about the the position of the youth of
ISA V the elders if it is a purely
strategic relationship and you mentioned
that your first conversation with Jordan
Hall you are like yeah when I got into
the business world it was actually
ethical but then the thing that remains
unsaid is that and then when my
generation took over the business world
it became completely unethical yep right
that which is the generation that
actually caused you know so it's it's a
striking thing and and so yeah so we're
I think we're in that situation when you
look at the educational reform dynamics
and the Predators to Delon ding and the
nature student loan market the predatory
student loan market and the nature of
the the d professionalization of a lot
of the work that's taking place now and
yeah it's it's hard to see what the
youth are gonna do in the next decade
and so i worry a lot actually about ways
to help to mitigate the most extreme
aspects of this educational crisis and
right now with the nature of the
situation with the pandemic we're
actually not in school the schools have
been shut down and most of the reports
I'm getting from teachers are that it's
not working great it's intently in my
book I suggest that all the schools
should have already put in place
something like a alternative educational
hub network right that when the buses
can't run and the lunches can't be
served in the cafeteria is there
something like a generator for the
educational system that you can shut the
physical infrastructure and boot the
digital infrastructure and then have
this backup system of a distributed kind
of educational hub network and none of
those were actually put in place even
though I had some conversations with
school districts suggesting they do it
you know like in Vermont there's you can
get a snow week in Vermont
you know because it dumps whatever to
feed or something and it's like for
those weeks the kids just simply aren't
in school and so the whole country was
basically asked to rapidly transition
into it completely distributed digitally
facilitated kind of stay-at-home school
system and it's mostly been an abject
failure although of course there's been
pockets of innovation and so what that
means is like you know these kids are
going to advance to the next grade
without actually having finished the
previous grade or not I mean there's
some talk that the right thing to do is
just have everybody do this last grade
over again which will have all kinds of
weird backups in the downstream system
including a whole lack of a freshman
year someplace oh yeah oh yeah it is
interesting that you know unfortunately
because we're a society that is reactive
and has driven by short-term money on
money return we do not invest in
robustness and this is one of the
fundamentally deep broken problems that
drives the meta-crisis and we're and
we're paying for it right now you know
if we'd had a department of wicked risks
for instance that could have tracked the
rise of the covetous had fully modeled
the other viruses and could have called
the play earlier we could reduce by
trillions of dollars the damage to our
economic system we could have had kids
back to school probably by the 1st of
May etc but because of the fact that we
invented on the fly only when absolutely
needed
we have paying way larger costs than we
need to
on these tail risks and again people who
don't understand that these kinds of big
events are relatively common so called
tail risk and the failure to understand
that is one of the greatest failings of
our epoch again probably driven by
education even those who are
well-educated PhDs in sociology or
business who have had lots of Statistics
all they're taught is gaussian
statistics right and if you all you know
is gaussian statistics you'll say
extreme events are extremely rare I
still remember being so pissed off
during a 2008 crisis some senior
executive from GE Capital said we can't
be held responsible this was a 16 Sigma
event meaning is you know once in a
hundred million years and I go idiot
only on a Gaussian distribution any
reasonable
of fluctuations in economic social
systems would say this is about a one in
a hundred year event right so shut the
fuck up asshole right and who the hell
let you be the CEO of you know many many
billions of dollars of capital assets
you know again about failure of
education into understanding that we
live in a complex world and that complex
systems thinking is an absolute
requisite for those who are gonna try to
steer our society or even exist in it in
fact one of things I did like about your
book at first I was hey no goddamnit
this is a guy with a hammer and
everything is that education nail but
you could come out and say quite
strongly that throughout the book you're
looking at the interdependence between
educational organizations teach early
practice and the rest of society and
culture and this idea of multiple
systems that are coupled in various ways
and have extraordinarily complex
nonlinear dynamics I thought was
something you could have done a little
bit more of in the book but you clearly
are informed by that perspective yeah
absolutely and it's a so we've been
talking about the schools and that's
where most people locate education and
I've been using the term
intergenerational transmission to try to
kind of signal that there's actually a
much deeper way to understand this
function of education which makes
schools actually a kind of relatively
new historical invention and that's a
whole other conversation but yeah I'm
coming from a complex systems view of
societal evolution and you know I
mentioned Wallerstein and he pulls on
Prigogine and background with the Santa
Fe Institute type you know Jeffrey west
and Ervin Laszlo and other people who
modeled social systems as basically Otto
poetically reproducing themselves in
terms of complex systems dynamics and so
as an intergenerational transmission is
basically the autopoietic function of
the social system which means that it
doesn't just happen in schools at all
and that in fact if I make a grocery
store the way grocery stores have been
made there's a hidden curriculum there
I'm transmitting to the next generation
something about what food is even though
I never mentioned in schools on the
curriculum same thing with energy
same thing with water transportation etc
so there's a deeper pattern of
intergenerational transmission which
john dewey noted early that all the
institutions and patterns of a society
are educated or educational as if that's
actually the definition of education I'm
working with not just schools in fact
I'm suggesting schools as we've known
them are basically obsolete you know
modern inventions which were useful in a
certain period of time but that are
basically decades past their prime of
efficiency for serving the autopoietic
regeneration of the social system so
it's important to see that yeah if you
can see vegetation that broadly then
you're actually looking at a range of
problems which are outside the scope of
just educational reform as we've usually
discussed it which means school reform
the most obvious one is the
informational ecology you know which has
in the last couple decades just become
probably the the main effect when you're
looking at people's capacities and
epistemic s' you know their frameworks
and their internal working models of who
they are and what the world is about and
when you look at adolescent culture
right now in conjunction with everything
we've talked about how the schools are
failed and in part because they're
obsolete in part because they can't
handle this exact problem which is how
do you stop the kids from getting
brainwashed by social media when the
freaking adults are brainwashed by
social media you know like I'm sure I'm
amazed that grown professionals with a
tremendous amount of other things to do
spend time on Facebook when they know
that it is built to be addictive and
that it is used to transmit micro
targeted advertisements to try to impact
you at an emotional level that it's a
extractive model of harvesting your time
attention and capability for their
profit
but we do it push back on that just a
little bit when I read some of your you
know attacks on our information
ecosystem about much by the way I do
agree that emergently in the majority of
actual humans in around the net result
of all this is somewhat surprisingly a
reduction in our sense making capability
however there are certainly trends that
point the other way Facebook being one
while you know open general Facebook is
just this you know useless and as you
say manipulative you are the product
you're being micro-targeted etc on the
other hand Facebook has also developed
an ecosystem or and the users really
pushed it which are the so called groups
I would say ninety percent at least
maybe more now of my time on Facebook is
in specialized groups of people who have
self organized in a network centric
fashion to pursue a specific agenda and
some of those agendas are radical social
change in fact at this point the core
hottest part of the game be movement is
on the game be group on Facebook about
2,000 members people from all kinds of
different areas growing exponentially
and I don't know if there's ads in
groups if they are they're unobtrusive
and I don't know what the help their
algorithms would make out of our game be
conversations on Facebook and now we
have decided that the core group had
gotten about two months ago two heavily
trafficked it was too many topics and so
we took one of the affordances of
Facebook which they don't even know
probably could be used for this we
created a game B page the game B page on
Facebook which then links to so far
about eighteen additional groups of game
be game be branded so we have game be
community building game be parenting
game be education game be communities
etc and so we have taken the tools
available that Facebook created for god
knows what reason and have molded them
to our own subversive purposes so that's
number one
you know even though open Facebook is a
cesspool it gets worse by the minute
Twitter is even worse in many ways
unless you're willing to spend a lot of
time on curation but these tools can be
used in the second one on you meant
Google as being problematic and I think
back as a nerdy smart working-class kid
who had depleted his school and
community libraries of every interesting
book on science by the time I was 11 if
someone had turned me loose with Google
Scholar when I was 12
holy shit I don't know what would have
become of me but I don't think it would
be bad
well the the temptations to go in
useless or worse than useless direction
certainly exist there are amazing things
on the Internet
you know the whole MIT curriculum is
available almost all of it available on
the Internet as our big parts of other
elite colleges again I use Google
Scholar many times a day and just
visualizing 12 year old 13 year old
nerdy gym rut you know following his
passion through a thread of scientific
articles you know is mind-blowing I
would have been a waste martyr person
way earlier if I'd had access to that
tool so it's not all bad in fact there's
lots really good and one that you slam a
little but I'd love to hear your
thoughts on that was Khan Academy again
when I first stumbled across the Khan
Academy ago god damn it I wish I'd had
access to that when I was 10 or 11 that
would have been amazing I had to listen
to these droning boring people who you
know spent three-quarters of each years
math class recapitulating last year's
why can't we move on son of a bitch is
with the Khan Academy I could have been
teaching myself calculus when I was 13
so there's a lot of good in our
information systems of course you know
and the overall recommendation of my
book is actually to transition out of
traditional brick-and-mortar schools
into a educational system that has you
know in massively new potentialities as
a result of embracing digital
technologies but there's this question
of you know what is actually educational
as opposed to just informational and
informational environments are not
necessarily educational environments and
so there's a complex thing that's
happened
we think that using digital technology
for education means getting kids to
stare at screens all day and it
absolutely doesn't need to be the case
and I have some design kind of
recommendations in my book for
educational technologies that would not
actually depend upon increased screen
usage and isolated you know kind of
autistic exploration through uncured
informational environments so that's one
factor which is that you know Khan
Academy is amazing actually think it's
an incredible resource but it is kids
starin at screens all day and that's not
what education is at a fundamental level
so the idea that you could roll out a
national digital curriculum which would
have kids sitting in front of computer
screens for seven hours a day and that's
education and it's actually better than
it used to be because they have access
to everything super naive right most of
Education happens in conversation with
actual other people in real space and
time and sensory motor development
aesthetic development ethical
development all of these things outside
of the merely cognitive and science
technology engineering and math domains
all of those things require real human
interpersonal contact so that's one -
you know I'm a rawls in so I actually
think in a very principled way about the
nature of justice and justice is about
the way basic institutions of society
kind of like set the conditions for
people to to work and thrive in and when
you're judging a system the best way to
judge is actually by taking into account
first and foremost the position of the
least well-off and so of course 13-year
old Jim Rotten would have done great
with Google and Google Scholar and my
sense is in fact you know even if that
Jim rut had access to Facebook he may
have been disciplined enough to not go
on Facebook or to use Facebook in this
really sophisticated way but
when you're look at what happens to
those kids who are not self directed
learners right who have trauma or who
are in other ways not talented enough to
turn an informational ecosystem into it
an educational ecosystem you get in a
situation where you look at what
Facebook does to those people who are
just captured by it all right so it's
like totally there's a park beautiful
park right people sell crack in the park
right but there are places in the park
where you can play basketball so you're
saying basically like hey we can play
basketball in this park and I'm saying
yeah but there's crack dealers in that
park I love that that I love that I'm
gonna steal at it well I'll give credit
but that's a perfect example of Facebook
it's a nice park
there's picnic tables you can take your
family because you know a lot people use
Facebook mostly to communicate with
their family tically boomers right and
so it's good but oh yeah there's crack
dealers and there's hypnotists they go
turn you into a sex criminal all kinds
of weird shit out there
no and it's and what I'm saying is like
I what most people know my Facebook's
actually open question right like show
us the data Facebook what are people
doing like the advertisers know what
most people do on Facebook but it's not
clear to me what is actually going on
there we know it drives depression we
know it drives addiction we know it
drives conspiracy theories we know it
drives lowering self-esteem and
adolescence and cyberbullying and a
whole bunch of other stuff so I'm not
saying like oh it's a nice Park and the
drug dealers are hiding there I'm saying
it's a park where drugs are dealt there
are places in it where it's maybe safe
but in order to get to those places you
have to walk through the places where
it's filled with drug dealers and it's
by design like Facebook brought in
people with an expertise in addiction to
help them think about design features
not that make them not addictive you
know the same way that fast-food
companies put chemicals to basically
make flavors that are radically
addictive and so this is by design that
it's capturing attention completely
distracting and destroying the epistemic
of the youth and some of the adults many
of the adults
oh yeah we've talked about this on the
show quite a bit in fact just recently I
did an episode with Steven Levy who
wrote a book about Facebook and he gets
into a lot of this and my friend Tristan
Harris was on the show and I think his
group Humane tech is doing some of the
very best work at theorizing and
capturing to the degree they can as you
point out the inner data is not
available but there's a fair amount of
scientific research that's been
published on facebook on how people are
using it and what it's actually doing to
us and some of those dimensions you
talked about you know teenage depression
teenage suicide may well be causally
linked the really big turn up is
suspiciously well correlated with the
introduction of the smartphone and the
proliferation of Facebook as the default
meeting ground for teens in you know the
2010 timeframe how about a pivot here
now a little bit - what I took away as
maybe the central theme of your book
which to use your words
the importance of rithi rising teacherly
authority and responsibilities and
contemporary educational configurations
this struck me as being very relevant to
the discussion about Google Scholar or
Google itself or Wikipedia as a resource
but without having something like
teacherly authority to help guide and
error correct and form the broader
contexts and indeed something would be
quite lacking in the you know sort of
self configuration that some people
might even the 13-year old gym rut would
have failed to do if they didn't have
excellent teacher Lee authority in some
form so I'd love to have you riff on
that one let me know if you think that's
close to your theme and second riff
pretty deeply on what a really good new
modern form of distributed teacher lee
authority might look like yeah so
teacher Lee authority yeah it is at the
at the root of the theorizing I do it in
the book it's actually the root of
resolving the educational crisis and
therefore the meta crisis it's something
like the reestablishing of a new kind of
teacher Lee a new kind of teacher Lee
authority and what's interesting is that
you know you actually don't get anything
like human culture without teacher Lee
Authority and I've you know made some
arguments based on the work of Michael
Tomasello who was at the Max Planck
Institute for a while as a comparative
psychologist looking at the differences
between primates and humans in
particular and although it doesn't put
it in these terms this is actually
definitely the conclusion of his work
which is something like there's a
species specific trait to the human to
homo sapiens sapiens and that species
specific trait which is the real
differentiator because there's so much
that we share with monkeys and other
primates and then even things like
whales and that is actually this teacher
Lee Authority that it's a specific kind
of intergenerational transmission which
is facilitated by joint attentional
awareness necessary you and me engaging
with something in a context where you
have greater knowledge and capacity and
I have less and we both know I'm trying
to learn from you this is the kind of
like species specific kind of like
anthropologically deep-seated kind of
like archetype of teaching and learning
and you know people have argued with
Michael Tomasello well no it's very
clear like monkeys teach other monkeys
and it's like yeah that's their their
you know the mother monkey we'll put the
stick in the anthill and bring out ants
and then leave the stick there and then
the kid will try it but there's nothing
like the complexity and abstraction of
joint attention that you get even in the
symbolist interaction with a toddler so
just a simple example is that monkeys
don't point
and you know he did a lot of research on
this in the you know like 20 years ago
and I'm sure other people have followed
up and there may be some complexity but
you know if I point to add something
most or look carefully most young humans
will follow my point and dogs follow
points because they've been involved
with us but in nature spontaneously
monkeys don't point for other monkeys to
follow and this is something about joint
attention and it's something about again
the the things that set humans apart and
allow for the kinds of civilizations
that we have where do those are sad they
reside in this dynamic of teacherly
Authority and the level and
sophistication of intergenerational and
cultural transmission that we can
facilitate and so when I'm saying with
all that is basically that when I say
teacherly Authority don't think like
teacher in a school don't think that at
all like that's we think teaching and
education we put them in schools but
that's this modern bias in fact teach
early Authority is a deeply rooted
aspect of what it means to be human and
we've had structures both formal and
informal of teach early Authority in
play for as long as we've been human and
in fact as soon as we start putting them
in play is when you could say oh okay
human and so they work as I described
and they're you know teaching a child to
tie a shoes interesting example but you
can do any number of them you have an
asymmetry of knowledge and capacity you
also tend to have an asymmetry of power
but a relationship is entered into
nonetheless where the person on the plus
side of that asymmetry which is say the
smarter more powerful person they are
taking the best interests in mind of the
younger person with them with a with an
intention to engage in teaching and vice
versa that the student the role of the
student also has to be you have to know
that you're in that situation so I'm not
talking about tacit learning and mere
imitation where you pick up things by
being around someone that's not too
the authority to Julie throws an
explicit relationship a kind of social
role dynamic and it hinges upon the
perceived legitimacy of the relationship
right so if I claim to have an asymmetry
of knowledge and power but in fact I
only have any symmetry of power then I
have pseudo teacherly Authority which
has been the big problem lately um where
I have actual a symmetry of knowledge
then you can actually have something
like legitimate teacherly Authority
because we've been in state-run
institutionalized schools where teachers
have teacherly authority by virtue of
power differential and maybe sometimes
knowledge differential but definitely by
virtue of power differential then you
lay the groundwork for slowly
undermining the ability to perceive a
legitimate teacherly authority so this
is what's important when people talk
about you know a working group coming
together and it's a bunch of people with
different capacities and then a
spontaneous hierarchy emerges within the
group it's not a bureaucratic hierarchy
it's a hierarchy of competence and skill
and we all want to be in those kinds of
situations but that relies upon the
ability of people to perceive actual
differences in capacity and fall into
line in terms of the dynamics of
teacherly Authority and so for example
right now I'm kind of holding forth with
teacherly Authority about teacherly
Authority how matter how meta but when I
when I go to the auto mechanic and he is
telling me about this problem with my
car and I'm asking questions like well
how does that actually work and then the
auto mechanic is on the up gradient of
the capacity differential he is
exercising teacherly authority over me
right and so it's not that it's like one
person is always in a position of teach
really Authority that's super
pathological it's actually these suit
very flexible
and dynamically shifting structures and
and it's the ability to basically create
containers and this is what it was is
the notion of a school right and the
notion of a place in society where
education takes place in particular
create these containers where legitimate
teacher the authority can be most easily
recognized and harnessed and where the
student and the teacher are able to fall
into the dynamics of trust and
interaction that are required so and
there's more to say so you can look also
as a developmental psychologist which
I've that's like my formal training you
can look at those capacity differentials
that lay the groundwork for teach early
Authority and can look at them very
specifically you know and it's most
clear and early childhood but even in
adulthood with high order conceptual
frameworks in and capacity acquisition
it's possible to to mark the learning
sequences that unfold in these different
domains and see where just how much more
knowledge does that person have right
like how legitimate is that teacher the
authority is it just that they have a
novel way of speaking and they're
charismatic or is it that there's
actually really a knowledge incapacity
differential and so those kinds of
discernments which need to be made on
the part of the student and the teacher
if they're honest and self reflective
those things need to be revealed and
thematized
and felt so i mentioned the problem with
teacher lee authority being based solely
on bureaucratic power but there's also
this problem which is more novel which
is teacher lee authority being based on
something like the popularity of a
platform or the number of likes or views
or celebrity status so I'm talking about
the transformation of teaching the
authority in the context of the digital
information Ecology's and
this is kind of what in the last couple
decades has actually brought what was
already an educational crisis to a head
which is that the water has become so
muddy in terms of how to detect
legitimate teach really Authority that
now we don't even know it when we see it
and when we do see it there's often a
knee-jerk reaction to destroy it that
teacher the authority is not wanted
and so now we're back to the
legitimation or legitimacy crisis which
is to say if you land in an
institutional situation where you've
undercut teacherly authority in the
places it needs to be able to show up
and be detected then you've undercut the
ability for intergenerational
transmission and if that goes long
enough then even when you come forward
as a legitimate teacher there's no one
who will assume the role of student and
some of this has had to do with kind of
the way the schooling and family
structures and other things have been
preyed upon so that much and back to the
education reductive human capital theory
that you know too often people
understand intergenerational
transmission strategically which doesn't
require entering into an actual
relationship with teach early
authorities so for example if I go to a
college like and I pay money to go to
college I'm actually taking out as much
as a house I'm like taking a mortgage
out as a 18 year old in order to go to
college and I'm making that decision
strategically because I want to go to
the college that's going to give me the
biggest return on that investment in
terms of future earnings right so this
is human capital theory so now I'm
sitting in the classroom and I'm super
aware that like every hour I mean this
classroom costs this much money because
I'm aware of that I took out $40,000 or
whatever probably even more it to be
sitting there and then the teacher
starts challenging me and the teacher
starts saying things that do disagree
with right and the teacher starts
inviting guest lecturers that say things
that I don't want to hear that
bother my identity right so now you're
in a situation where student has
consumer disrupts the ability to be
student as the learner disrupts the
ability of student to actually get in a
relationship of teacherly authority so
what I'm saying is that and this is my
notion of the education commodity
proposition that you know consumers are
always right the customer's always right
students want to be proven wrong so for
as long as we hold the educational
interactions and intergenerational
transmission in the frame of commodity
exchange and strategic intergenerational
relationship for return on investment of
education that we actually have really
made quite and fragile and delicate
where does teacher Lee authority
actually arise in those contexts right
it's like in the back rooms it's like
the random you know fortuitous
student-teacher relationship that
emerges it's not systemic it's just
what's systemic in the system is this
strategic relation between generations
almost as a form of commodity exchange
and so similarly it's like you know a
lot of teacher Lee authority resides
with some mother if I knew that my mom
was my mom because she was getting paid
by the state let's say right this has
been recommended like your mom didn't
get paid to take care of you when you
were little gym rat now should the state
have paid her to do that and then
actually monitored her behavior and paid
her more if she was like a quote good
mom right ah fuck bad right I'm saying
so it's like that actually would be the
most devastating undermining of
intergenerational transmission you could
imagine because it would undermine the
intergenerational transmission of love
right there's this question okay my
mom's nice to me why is my mom nice to
me cuz she loves me but then in the back
of your mind there'd be this
oh no she's actually being nice to me
because she's virtue signaling to the
monitors who will pay her more all right
and so you have to understand how much
we were approximating this kind of
situation in many institutional contexts
where intergenerational transmission
takes place and the
undermining again just to reiterate the
undermining of teacherly authority has
ramifications out into all of the other
aspects of our institutional structures
and there's no way for example to get
out of the political crisis we're in
right now like with the Congress and the
Senate and the president of the voting
and all that stuff if you want to call
that politics that whole situation
hinges on this notion of legitimate
teacherly Authority the whole problem
with the informational ecosystem with
kind of fake news and alternative facts
and conspiracy is and then also like the
blue church kind of like homogenized
kind of like New York Times all of that
is in question because teacherly
Authority itself is in question so yeah
we have to find a way to get into a
position where we can first recognize
this problem and then create new
contexts in which actual teacherly
Authority can re-emerge
yeah that's great I mean that is the
heart of your book that I took away from
it that you know as we move the world
towards a better and new social
operating system a nuanced and
distributed and non-dogmatic form of
teacherly authority broadly construed
and that's and you make that point
several times not somebody standing in
front of 30 kids
tapping on their desk with their ruler
is gonna be absolutely essential to make
this not only an intergenerational
transfer but because we're living in a
world where there's a demand for
exponential increase in capacity it has
to be an intergenerational upgrade
between each generations which makes the
problem even more difficult now if you
don't mind I got a few things I wanted
to hit on that these comments brought
forth one the tight linkage between
teacherly Authority and parenting you
mentioned it in places in the book but I
didn't find that you developed it in a
really rich fashion and you could
probably say more about that I'll give
you a chance to do that in a bit and you
mentioned the criticality of mothers no
doubt in my mind the most influential
person in my life was my mother she was
a great person in her own way we were up
at a house without electricity or indoor
plumbing left home when she was 14 made
her way to DC when she was 16 saved up
nickels dimes and quarters from being a
waitress but she was a great person in
her own way and I would not be who I was
without her and you know the fact that
she was able to ask you status through
stuff was what her allowed her to do
that and all three of her kids got to
say we all had great lives and really
solid citizens been very successful in
our own very different domains and
basically because we had that great
experience so I can also point out and
get another anecdotal story of my wife
she taught headstart for a year and part
of headstart was doing family visits and
so they visited the families of all the
students at the end of the year she quit
for two reasons one during the time she
was working at Head Start she read the
research which showed that Head Start
didn't stick and then the family visits
told her that sorry these families are
so dysfunctional
couple of years where the Head Start is
not gonna make much a deaf
and so parenting and you know capacity
in the family has got to be intimately
crafted as part of this social operating
system of teacherly authority my next
point is and you point this out
specifically in your book that there are
trends of so-called hyper progressive
reforms like unschooling or one I'm
familiar with raw learning or makerspace
based learning learning by imitation
essentially where the teacher Lee
Authority is very much downplayed and
well I think some of that is good I'm
with you that you know as a full way to
educate the next generation and do that
intergenerational upgrade of capacity
that does not strike me as likely to be
successful and third the one you in your
nice discussion there pointed to this
undermining of all authority and
particularly teacher Lee authority and
parental authority there are a lot of
crazy-ass fuckin theories running around
about parental authority right there are
actually people who would advocate which
we both laughed at I think I went beyond
laughing the idea of paying the mother
and having social workers come in and
assessor once a quarter and giving her a
grade give her a bonus I mean what the
fuck right but there are people
advocating that and it strikes me that
an awful lot of that rot comes from the
capture of a fair amount of our academia
particularly in education departments by
what I call post modernists people who
have lost their way in thinking about
reality and have kind of generated these
bizarre theories within theories that
just are not practical that have no real
traction with the real world and
particularly in education schools those
things have made considerable progress
and have led to some really pretty crazy
shit I give you one personal experience
I was after I stepped down as chairman
of SF I moved back to Virginia I started
living at my farm again I took on a gig
as a consultant to a major research
university which will remain unnamed who
wanted to establish a PhD
cross-disciplinary ph.d program in
cognitive science they had one of the
top undergraduate psychology programs in
country and they wanted to upgrade it to
a ph.d program and so I helped them for
quite a while and we found tremendous
support from all the other schools from
medical school nursing school
engineering school for their computer
science department even the business
school but when we went to call on the
Dean of the School of Education and the
department heads of a couple of the sub
departments it was like we were like
aliens from Uranus coming here to sell
them some kind of crazy shit and what we
were trying to sell was I would say
state-of-the-art cognitive neuroscience
and cognitive science and we looked at
the courses they were offering and
things like educational psychology and
we were all saying this is 50 year old
stuff and some of it wouldn't even have
been considered good psychology 50 years
ago and you know I didn't know it at the
time but the other folks that were more
knowledgeable than I about the politics
of Education you know again they pointed
to the fact that you know that
particular school had been taken over by
postmodernists than therefore had
descended into a mouse room of nonsense
and that we should not waste our time
talking to him and we didn't so anyway
that's a number of reactions I like to
get your reactions to my reactions
there's a lot there so I mean the post
modernists took over a lot of the
university system and especially those
departments that were again kind of
least well-off you know education has a
field has been on the defensive
basically since it began and the trend
has been scientific experts who are men
come in and tell women who have 30 years
of experience with young children that
they're doing it wrong and there's a
more scientific way for them to do it
and if you look at the history of the IQ
testing movement which is intimately
tied to the eugenics movement which is
intimately all tied to the birth of our
large-scale public education systems the
United States as part of the
urbanization and
immigration that was occurring you know
this is just pre-world War one
you're looking at a unconscionable
intervention into the life world with a
ostensibly but mostly bullshit
scientific instrument running roughshod
over the dynamics of teacherly Authority
and so it's not a surprise to me that as
post-modernism emerged it took uh
presidents most rudely in certain
graduate schools of education because
you know post-modernism began as a set
of extremely valid criticisms against
what watch they hyper omniscient and
reductive form of modernism and the
question of you know how a critique that
was simply deconstructive could ever be
transformed into something that was
reconstructive remains open so i guess
i'm you know and i encountered this
myself so i was in the head Teaching
Fellow briefly of a mind brain and
Education Department
that's a Harvard Graduate School of
Education it was founded by my adviser
kurt fischer who actually recently just
passed away one of the most brilliant
developmental psychologists ever but it
was the first program of its kind which
was a program in a graduate school of
education integrating cognitive science
neuroscience and pedagogics basically
education and there was tremendous
resistance tremendous in part and I came
to detect it as part of this narrative I
was just telling him part it was a fear
it was a fear that we would based on the
latest trendy scientific findings about
the brain override decades of intuitive
tacit knowledge accumulated by underpaid
teachers right that we would and this
has happened this is in part what the
field of educational neuroscience turned
into in certain areas it it turned into
brain based education
was using scientific findings that were
specious and would be overturned within
a year using them to think about
rebooting whole curriculums right it's
just foolish it's completely foolish
education is not a technical problem so
science only could choose so far and the
version many teachers have and of course
the post modernists in particular gives
them kind of like some ammunition to to
ratify these arguments I think more than
they should the resistance comes from
that long history of Education being
basically the least well off of the
institutions so yeah so that's some of
the way I think it makes sense to read
that situation and then there's that
question of what why is education the
least well-off given that it's so
freakin important right and this is a
really interesting question and when you
look especially at the history of
educational reform in the United States
you're seeing the public education
systems and that means the teachers
within them right who have always been
and remained although a little bit less
so primarily women who are underpaid
given their skill capacity these
educational systems have been the
hobbyhorse of the industrial elite
philanthropic classes and that needs to
be noted as well when you're looking at
well why did the post modernists take
over the Education Department it's
because the education has got the most
screwed by the kind of over
reductionistic human capital theory
modernist views of Education so that is
unfortunate but unless there's a major
change in the way we understand the
value of education and we actually make
education something more like being a
lawyer or a doctor or a CEO unless we do
that there's there's no way to
resuscitate the degree of teacherly
authority that's needed to right
to ship at this point the wooden your
theory say rather than a doctor type
teacher I thought you were talking about
the idea of spreading teacher Li
Authority much more widely you know into
the hands of the local expert in Y also
puts on his teacher Li Authority hat
teach the aspiring fourteen-year-old a
little bit of rudimentary thermodynamics
totally or the mother who puts on the
teacher Li Authority hat to say here's
how you do a fickle reasoning etc and
maybe there's not a need for a doctor
like person at least in the lives of you
know I wasn't suggesting that they are
understood as having a kind of like
special class of expertise I was I was
suggesting that day that it's perceived
as a social good actually
that there's a prestes associated with
being good at conducting
intergenerational transmission right
doesn't mean your need to be renew marae
today we're enumerate you know brain
surgeons or whatever but it doesn't mean
that there is a in cultural perception
about the value of what's taking place
in these spaces that needs to that needs
to happen because they've been spaces
that have been subject to capture by
forces that have not educational
interest in mind but again these
reframing zuv the full spectrum of what
education needs to be in terms of this
reductive human capital limiting it and
yeah so that's that's kind of they're
like the state of graduate schools of
education is bad that they have been
taken over by post modernists but that's
because they've been in this position of
the least well-off you know yeah they
went from the fire to the fire pay and
ever you know incompetent social
engineers and then they went to just
utter insane nonsense or I hardly
progress but it's understandable yeah
it's funny because it's like the
teachers aren't incompetent social
engineers it's it's the people who came
in thinking they knew better than the
teachers yeah and thinking specifically
and in a sense they did know better than
the teachers about how to make the
school system reproduce human capital
but they didn't know better than the
teachers about how to have the school
system reproduce human being is that can
actually perpetuate a civilization in
perpetuity so that's the one and then
I'm remembering the parenting one what
was the one in the middle what's the
tendency among some people consider
themselves educational progressives to
move towards unschooling or raw learning
or maker based learning that's basically
imitative yeah I mean I'm I'm definitely
in the kind of like unschooling
movement like my book is I'm
resuscitating Ivan Illich is arguments
about D schooling society but I'm doing
that in the interest of teacher Li
Authority not as a protest against it
and basically saying that because the
schools have run the way that they've
run for so long it's going to be very
hard to create the conditions conducive
to teach really Authority in those
contexts because it's like as soon as a
kid walks into the school if he is a
reflective adolescent if he's not trying
to be strategic and get into college and
he's just being honest about what's
going on in the school
it's what graver would call a bullshit
job right what goes on in the school
you're doing busywork right you're
mostly could take the learning that
you're getting and do it in a couple
hours a day which are there for six
hours a day and the projects are all
abstract the projects aren't having you
use your skills to help the community
around you they're you having to use
your skills to get yourself promoted to
get into a college to maybe eventually
get a job which then you can help the
community right so there's this
postponing of meaningful work and that's
one again the other things that
undermines teacherly Authority so I'm in
favor of dismantling the schools
creating something like an educational
hub network in which there's distributed
teach really Authority but that requires
contexts in which teach really Authority
can appear and that means context where
younger people and older people are
engaged with actual meaningful problems
together where both have an interest in
solving the problem so no more bullshit
in the schools there's so much work to
do there's so many problems to solve
that it's ridiculous we're having kids
take tests that have no relation
chip to the world when we could have
them in apprentice like relationships in
kind of neo guild like structures where
as soon as they're able to they're
helping the community under the guidance
of more knowledgeable elders building
skill and also contributing and so
makerspaces and radically kind of like d
authoritarian or anti-authoritarian
homeschooling and things like that are
reactive they're not gonna help us in
the long run but they are kind of
pockets like temporary autonomous zones
in the educational space where you can
get in and actually do amazing things
because in those contexts spontaneous
legitimate teach really Authority can
arise where it's actually
disincentivized from arising in schools
often it's it's another conversation
about how scripted some curriculums
actually are and how the standardized
testing infrastructures in particular
make it so that were legitimate teacher
Lee authority to arise it would be seen
as suspect and maybe potentially
undermining the kind of metrics by which
the school is is gauged but in these
autonomous areas where education is
occurring much more spontaneously there
still can't happen
but if we start to design for it to
happen and again think about ways to
create context where real legitimate
meaningful teach really Authority can
arise then we're in a different
situation so I do think that you know so
think about it it's like if you watch
Fox News then anytime you see something
on CNN or the New York Times you're not
going to buy it you're not gonna buy
into the teacherly authority of the New
York Times simply because it's the New
York Times and vice versa so if you're a
kid and you've learned over the course
of grade school and maybe up into middle
school that
these teachers aren't really all they're
cracked up to be and I don't understand
why I have to learn this instead of that
and you know you're basically seeing
through some of the illusion of school
and then you in a school encounter a
teacher who's legit
you're gonna discount them simply by
virtue of the fact that they're in a
school right so I really think that
we've gone quite far down of trajectory
that has undermine teach really
Authority in the schools and I blame the
standardized tests primarily because
everyone knows that the interests of the
teachers actually to get the kids to do
well on the tests even if he loves the
kids all right and there's this
potential and she's super smart and
there's a potential for real authentic
teacher Lee Authority to emerge at the
end of the day the overarching
motivation of the school and everyone in
it is to pass tests that have a very
specific content and a very specific
assessment type of modality and again
that's highly unnatural from the
perspective of intergenerational
transmission whereas if you're an
apprenticeship model and you're
concretely working every day on the
problems together that you both care
about you don't need a standardized test
at the end every day there's multiple
assessment instances there's multiple
assessment engagements and conversations
and learning that's taking place so
that's that's a little bit on that and
then yet parenting is in a sense the
other place where education has been
kind of relegated to in the modern world
right so we think of like the schools
and we think of the home and these are
the places that are like saddled with
the burden of accomplishing democracy
right and so blame the teachers blame
the moms if you want to figure out
what's wrong but what you have to
understand about the breakdown of family
structures is that it's not a moral
failing it's at the level of the
individuals in the family it's a moral
failing at the level of the society
which allows society to exist with this
much for example inequitable
distribution
right so the question of why your wife
when she went in to the Head Start home
visits why those families were so
dysfunctional
it's a macroeconomic question what
immediately confront you is a
psychological and sociological question
questions about attachment theory
questions about trauma and things of
that nature
but if you pull out and look for the
generator function of families like that
it's not in a moral failing of the
individual it's in the moral failing of
the society and so again I am hugely
support the notion that the family is
actually at the core of civilizational
redesign but that is the most dangerous
thing to say as well and so here's what
I'm basically getting at which is that
the insight that the family is so
important is what leads to the insanity
of wanting social workers to monitor
every mother and wanting there to be
parenting licenses and parenting
mandatory parenting curriculum and these
kinds of things that's the most
Orwellian shitshow you can possibly
imagine if you have a civilization
that's micromanaging familial life right
the need to micromanage familial life
only takes place if the environments in
which families grow are devoid of
nutrients right which is to say like if
you plant a family in a cultural and
social contexts where normal healthy
human interaction isn't possible then
you have to go in and try to force them
to do that if you could create enough
and then back to my social miracles
chapter if you could create enough
surrounding the family then you could
actually ask people to step into the
responsibility of being in a family
instead what you're doing is asking
people to step into the responsibility
of contributing to the economy and then
the family takes on the externalities of
that right the families one of the
places and actually literally the minds
and the brains of the youth are part of
the places where we actually deposit the
externalities of our current social
system and so until we flip that then
there's there's no use and actually kind
of like
lamenting the state of parenting and
getting angry and irresponsible parents
and all of that stuff and that's usually
stuff that's said by like middle-class
white people you know like it's when you
really look at the situation with the
families you have to look first and
foremost so what the hell is the
economics around this family and you
know in Vermont like you've got
generational rural poverty generational
rural poverty which has to do with a lot
of things like agricultural subsidies
and changes in manufacturing locations
and all that stuff probably similar to
rural Virginia and what you have our
families and situations that are
basically it's extremely difficult to to
understand how these how these folks
actually get by let alone how they
manage to have loving conversations
around dinner tables reliably and you
know there is some sense that those are
the same people who are also you know
voting for Trump and who are also not
believing in climate change and who are
you know so there's this like cluster of
things which are occurring which we like
to read as almost like there's the moral
failings of these people and similar to
the way when a child struggles in school
we blame the child and eventually we
blame their brain and we give them ADHD
medication right it never occurs to us
to blame the school when the child fails
it's certainly it's certainly the last
place I would put attention is on the
child's nervous system the first thing I
would look at is the context in which
the child is trying to do the work
and so similarly with with the need to
think about how to help families and how
to kind of like revivify the virtue and
value of family life and I think for the
sake of intergenerational transmission
and true teacherly Authority and just
like sanity same argument as education
reform right don't focus on the school
don't focus on the family focus on what
is
pounding it focusing on all the things
that use the family to offload
externalities that use the family as a
point of extraction and rent-seeking the
families preyed upon
and yet we blame the family for the
breakdown of family values and so yeah
that's some of my view and it's similar
it's like I don't blame the schools for
the failure of democracy and there
there's a huge potential scapegoat
teachers in particular huge potential
scapegoats
when everyone pointing fingers at them
should actually be pointing fingers with
themselves usually business leaders etc
yeah so that's a little bit more on your
reactions me yeah I say that fits in to
what we talked about earlier about the
complex coupled systems nature of the
problem there is no one point fix in a
complex system typically right and at
least our game be fair is we have to Co
evolve our institutions and our people
together more or less over probably two
or three generations to solve these
problems no silver bullets right
unfortunately we're getting kind of far
into our time here and as we discussed
prior to show time we're gonna do a
second episode probably in a month or
two and hit the other half of my topic
notes Zacks book is so rich I just
recommend you should read it there's no
way we can do a justice in one 90-minute
session but one last topic I think this
is one that a lot of people will find
interesting and scary and controversial
and lots of other things before we wrap
up today you write very passionately
about the pharmacological ization of K
through 12 education and particularly
this proliferation of ADHD and similar
diagnoses particularly for boys in the K
to 12 system and the attempts to douse
them with various chemicals and that is
being a canary in the coal mine at least
and maybe even more than that so why
don't you talk a little bit about the
pharmacal is Asian and medicalization of
K to 12 education
totally and this is of course a very
controversial topic right when I've
spoken about ADHD medication ad D the
rapid not quite exponential but probably
now with the pandemic approaching
exponential growth rates of psychotropic
drug prescription to children when I
speak about these things I often get a
lot of pushback it's interesting
and the push backs on multiple levels
some of it comes from confusion about
the nature of what a disease entity is
and the nature of how the brain works
and how these drugs actually act on the
nervous system but some of it comes from
the perceived dire situation of many
young people within the schools and the
perception that failing in the schools
ends up having ramifications for the
rest of your life so what this means is
that those people who will probably
react to what I'm gonna unfold here I
have tremendous sympathy in fact for
just how dire the situation is for many
young boys in schools and understand the
the kind of almost overwhelming sense of
obligation one has as a parent sometimes
as a teacher or administrator to try to
help those kids like whatever it takes
and what I'm trying to do when I speak
about these things is provide a language
that can be used to kind of make better
sense of what the decision is we're
actually making when we decide to put a
child on a psychotropic drug to
positively impact educational
performance and so you mentioned it in
this if it comes down the medicalization
of academic underperformance
is the issue right so the medicalization
of academic underperformance turns the
dynamic of teacherly Authority
almost
necessarily into a strategic one and it
ends up undermining a whole bunch of the
conditions for the possibility of
certain forms of identity formation in
certain forms of intergenerational
transmission so I'm actually not going
to talk about the science of ADHD and
the dynamics of psycho psycho
pharmacological interventions from a
scientific standpoint you know it's
worth saying that and this gets back to
the broader crisis of teacherly
Authority it's worth saying that there
has been a massive tendency for bias
within ADHD research and you know I'm
not gonna get into a broader
conversation about you know how
pharmaceutical companies run and the
nature of direct to consumer
advertisements and you know the nature
of where publications that go through
certain journals come from but we know
those stories and how they play out and
it's not conspiracy it's actually just I
think easily findable knowledge so for
what I'm going to speak about is the
kind of difference between the raising
of children and the designing of
children and this actually brings
together a bunch of the themes we've
been talking about so I'm going to try
to kind of do this justice and the the
five or so minutes I have left so the
basic idea is that legitimate authentic
teach really Authority as I've described
it is a process of raising a child into
their unique self right it's a it's a
process of collaborative intent non
strategic interaction where the interest
of the child and the interest of the
adult align that there's a shared
educational goal between them which
matters to both of them and good
parenting you can feel it when you see
it in the interaction between the parent
and
child that the learning and development
that's taking place in that relationship
is not being imposed upon the child it's
not being done to the child it's being
done for and with the child so that's
raising children right but since Skinner
basically and then of course when you
get at into the like decade of
biomedical science and then the human
genome projects and other things there's
been this notion that we could actually
design children and I'm not kind of
saying like this is some science fiction
scenario I'm saying this is actually a
particular way of relating to children
intergenerationally where you do end
around the normal dynamics of teacherly
Authority and directly strategically
intervene into the biological substrate
of the child in the interest of
perpetuating one view which is the view
of the older generation right and so
hopper Moss Jurgen Habermas great German
social philosopher writes about this in
a book called the future of human nature
and he talks about it he's basically
saying like you know most of
intergenerational transmission and most
of the way civilization has evolved has
been on the organic life world
communicatively rich intergenerational
transmission where you're negotiating
and sharing joint attention working with
working for but we're approaching the
potential for an asymmetric a unilateral
strategic intervention into the
biological substrate of the up and
coming generation which would actually
short-circuit the ability to work with
and work for and only be working on
right and so reframing academic
difficulties and struggles as medical
problems transfers the locus of
intervention from the cultural dynamics
and communicative and interpersonal
dynamics teacherly Authority
to the biomechanical dynamics of
strategic intervention and so basically
kind of like regardless of if these
things actually work and by the way it's
not like open question it's a longer
conversation there's this question of
what's the right way to actually frame
intergenerational relationships is it
one where we work with them and for them
for the needs and ends that they have in
which we help them shape together
collaboratively or is intergenerational
transmission strategic they're gonna do
what we want them to do even if we have
to drug them right as you have to step
back in any context where someone's
struggling in academic context and look
at the dynamics of teacherly Authority
first is their shared learning goals is
their shared understanding of context
and motivation is there enough
communication and transparency where
both parties know that the interests of
the younger person are being kind of
basically understood or is it a dynamic
of teaching Authority where the kid
actually has no idea why this matters
except that he'll get punished or he
won't advance if he doesn't do well he
doesn't actually share the goal of the
teacher with what he wants to be doing
with his time right so the teacher wants
me to be studying this thing he doesn't
understand he wants to be talking to his
friend and you actually haven't given
him a good reason of why he shouldn't
accept some conventional reason that you
need to work hard in school alright so
for as long as the school system is
actually demonstrably irrational to the
perceptions of the child that it's very
hard to talk about anything like a
disease entity of attention deficit
disorder you actually need to give him a
reason to pay attention and that means
you need to create enough context of
legitimate teach really Authority where
it where it is felt to matter in an
embodied sense so instead of that
equation being run where we start to
look at the culture of schools where I
start to look at the dynamics of teach
really Authority and you know the
psychologies of
and the dynamics of you know the unrest
that occurs when the perception of
bullshit work sets in we're not looking
at that what we're doing instead is
claiming that the kid has a genetically
predetermined biological dysfunction in
his nervous system that's akin to a
disease entity that needs to be treated
with biomedical intervention for the
rest of his life right what was
happening was that school wasn't working
for him but what ends up getting the
understanding why what's understood by
the family the kid et cetera is that
this kids nervous system is basically
broken and I've had people tell me that
kids need ADHD medication like diabetics
need insulin right and this is a
completely erroneous view but it is held
and there's been some research into like
the self conceptions of kids who've been
medicated on ADHD medication and they
buy this they believe that their nervous
systems are broken that they were
genetically disadvantaged and so that
right there is an example of why the
postmodernists took over the edge
schools because you had a team of you
know you have this kind of like strange
symbiosis between kind of like medical
experts and pharmaceutical companies and
school administrators and other things
happening that are you know radically
stigmatizing and running interference on
reasonable self conceptions in
adolescents and turning what is actually
a political and cultural problem into a
medical problem and so that's just
endemic and actually it expands beyond
just academic struggles into you know a
lot of the terrain that is constituted
by psychopharmacology in general the D
politicization of deviance and the
medicalization therefore of deviance is
a really sticky wicket and so we're
going way far down that line and when
you hear you know people from the blue
church and
and the East and the West Coast and the
New York Times readers talking about how
the Trump supporters are actually insane
and should be medicated and things of
that nature and you end up realizing
that you know the same slope that we set
down on when we medicalised academic
kind of performance we can actually
expand that and go down and even
slippery slope and start trying to
medicalize any view we disagree with in
any lifestyle that doesn't make sense to
us so we need to much more carefully
disentangle the way we look at cultural
and social problems in our institutions
and the knee-jerk reaction to biomedical
intervention in the schools for academic
struggles and the diagnostic creep and
that's just the sheer number the kids
getting put on these drugs it's an
experiment of a massive scope because we
actually don't know enough about the
long-term effects and again it feels
like generational warfare to me where
instead of raising these kids right and
actually grappling with the problems
that they have and grappling with the
institutions that are not working for
them and the future job markets that are
not there and the meaning crisis that
has been created around them instead of
grappling with all that we're just gonna
make them do it
yep brute force drives me a little bit
of Thomas's Aza's critique of the
psychiatric movement of the 50s and 60s
which basically housed a million people
in insane asylums right and he pointed
out wait a minute we may have this
backwards right this may be an
indictment of our society I strongly
believe that about this medicalization
pharmacological ization of school I mean
that ought to be a screaming sign
there's something seriously wrong with
schools right and particularly that it's
gender very unequal it's at 15% of boys
and maybe 2% of girls or something are
on these things right but if you if you
expand it beyond ADHD medication you
realize that think the girls are just on
different meds for anxiety in yeah
they're on antidepressants and things
like that sort yeah but but I would also
say that hey you know being a guy who
like to dabble in his drugs and his
misspent youth speed works motherfucker
right
I wouldn't want to do it for very long
term and the idea of doing adderall for
15 years what the fuck right but you
know doing a few lines of crystal go out
and party hell yeah alright well that's
worth understanding is that these are
class two substances like this is
basically speed and you know ridden
Ritalin and Adderall have surpassed
alcohol and marijuana has substances
abused on college campuses on and so
yeah is worth people knowing that
actually this is just speed what's
interesting is that in the Army you know
the Nazis were actually the first ones
to weaponize and send amine cap industry
how could those some bitches march like
that surgery so that's where it starts
and of course the IQ testing also starts
with the Nazis people don't realize it
but so then the Americans emulate that
in the military with the IQ testing and
these and the amphetamines and then they
bring both the amphetamines and the IQ
testing into the schools now that people
also forget the Nazis got their ideas of
eugenics from the American yet so
Margaret Sanger those people they were
like big-time you genesis of a homicidal
variety is really not pretty exactly one
last thing here and then I think we'll
wrap up again and this issue that these
problems seem to be infecting boys more
than girls strikes me as real and it
resonates with one of my very favorite
books from David Graeber
called utopia of rules where the you
know late game a everything becomes a
fucking rule right you know nobody has
discretion about anything anymore
everything is black and white and highly
bureaus and I believe that that has had
a gigantic negative impact of the
experience of boys particularly in
schools again I'll use my own life as an
example fortunately prior to all his
horseshit you know for instance we
started carrying knives I think when I
was in third grade I had a Cub Scout
knife I always had in my pocket and by
the time you got to junior high school I
had a really cool knife that an
electrician friend of my father's gave
me was beautifully made case knife and
then in high school by senior year a
significant percentage of the boys
considered a standard part of manly
dress was a folding buck knife big old
buck hunter
on your belt with a leather scabbard
have you imagined if half the boys in a
public high school showed up with buck
knives on their belts they'd call out
the fucking National Guard they wouldn't
bother calling the police right another
one of my pet peeves is no fighting
right
yes fighting was against the rules when
we were kids and depending on the
context you know worst case you might
get three days suspension but you know
more likely get five days after school
one hour detention or something like
that but you know adolescent boys spar
you know look at the equivalent of any
kind of primate or frankly a lot of
mammals sparring amongst adolescent boys
is part of life and the idea we're gonna
have no fighting zero tolerance all the
fucking police what kind of hell mole
shit is that finally this might even be
the worst of them and they're all bad in
my opinion for boys but the reduction in
the amount of recess in elementary
school you know boys are high-energy
they're fidgety and again they want to
establish boy kingdoms right and you
know I will honestly say I believe I
learned more in recess in elementary
school and I did in the classroom and
particularly the stuff that was most
useful in my business career you know
how to organize you know what is culture
even right what are real friends for and
so this utopia of rules and everything
being you know teach to the test no
recess because we might put our
standardized test points scores up by
one percent strikes me is all being very
disadvantageous to an honest at normal
boyhood hmm you know I obviously
completely agreed that the disappearance
of recess and spaces for relatively
unsupervised play during grade school is
actually a very serious problem from the
perspective of moral development
and there's a lot to say there but if
kids don't have the freedom to
creatively resolve their own
interpersonal problems without adult
intervention then they never actually
get to exercise the muscles that are
necessary that kind of cognitive muscles
that are necessary to later in life be
autonomous moral reason errs so it's
it's both the physical activity of
recess that's
important like completely like please
don't put kids on ADHD meds you know
like give them freaking recess like it's
just like a no-brainer and also their
diet and all unsleep and other things
that that factor there but even deeper
than that I think is the absence of the
freedom and spaces for as you said
children to create culture without adult
supervision and this is again the
raising verse designing thing the desire
to control every aspect of the young
child's life tends towards design
whereas the ability to create safe
contexts in which kids can be free to
explore what spontaneously arises in
their native kind of like child cultures
that's what raising a kid is if you
truly love something right you set it
free there's something that is passive
aggressive and neurotically controlling
in the way that were you know limiting
the freedoms of children and you know
the utopian of rules book the Utopia of
rules book by graver that book was a
revelation to me because he was
articulating things that I'd been seeing
in my studies of standardized testing
and bureaucratization processes within
school systems and understand a lot of
this is also legal a lot of this has to
do with it I kind of like the
litigiousness of society that it's it's
not even that they care about this kids
is that they don't want to get sued
exactly and so you have to look again
it's not just that the schools in the
school are changing it's that the
ecosystem of legal precedents around the
school has shifted so that schools are
extremely vulnerable and the behaviors
of children are not outside of the kind
of litigious calculus of adult authority
figures so there's a there's a complex
set of things that is basically fenced
in the youth and again back to the
generational warfare it's not a
coincidence that the boomers in
particular be like hey remember all that
freedom that we had when we were kids to
like work together as adolescents to
throw to overthrow the adults
let's not have that happen again let's
make it so that there is no chance for
these kids to become sovereign agents
and that they are designed by us more or
less to perpetuate the economic system
that we created which it manages us and
systemically disadvantages them and that
begins with taking away recess and
taking the spirit out of the boys who
would otherwise have been leaders of men
yeah don't let them fight I mean here
you want to turn guys into capons don't
let them fight when they're 14 years old
right I know if you want school shooters
that's another nice way to do it right
well I think we've covered some amazing
ground here this has been one of the
most interesting conversations I've had
on the gym rut show I really want to
thank you for the depth in which we went
into and the very excellent back and
forth and I look really forward to
picking up on the second half of my
topic lists and doing this again at
about a month
sounds good Jim this has been a blast I
appreciate your listing
[Music]
production services and audio editing by
jerod Jane's consulting music by Tom
Muller at my